A Guide to the Charlottesville, Albemarle County and Vicinity, Miscellaneous Accounts, 1817-1897
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Charlottesville, Albemarle County and Vicinity, Miscellaneous Accounts 1817-1897
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-3
23 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content
A miscellaneous collection of accounts, originating, so far as is known, in Charlottesville and Albemarle County, except one from Rockingham County. Most were kept by unidentified merchants dealing in general merchandise. In several ledgers, two or more sets of accounts occur, as for instance in a ledger first kept apparently by a tavern keeper, with accounts for meals, lodging, and fodder (1817-1846), then by a grocer in Rockingham County (1864), and finally by a grain merchant (1869-1870). There are various accounts of Charlottesville or Albemarle merchants, of Spooner and Keller (1873-1867), J.W.B. McAllister (1875- 1879), tailor (1835), a painter and glazier (1859-1862), a miller (1860-1867), and stationers (1869-1873). There are also some official records of the jailer of Albemarle County (1874-1876), of T.L. Michie as an assignee in bankruptcy (1871-1879), a list of Charlottesville voters (1871), and reports of the Charlottesville police (1893-1895). Records of Wayland and Thompson of Free Union and of Seamands and Marchall are found both in this collection and in 38-4.
Contents List
- Account book 1817-1870 (Volume [1])
  Accounts, N.P., for meals, lodging, fodder; barn land etc., 1817-1818 (with occasional insertions of 1844, 1846, perhaps tallies of meals served?); 1846 June, accounts, Rockingham and N.P. for sales of groceries, cloth, nails, etc.; 1869-1870, accounts N.P. with A.G. Raynes for grain cloth
- Lawyer's fee book, perhaps of A.G. Ruffin whose name is on the first page, or F.G. Ruffin 1821-1839 (or 1840) (Volume [2])
- Account books 1835, 1874-1876 (Volume [3])
  A tailor's account book, Charlottesville; 1874-1876 account book of W.C. Walstrum, jailor of Albemarle County
- Account book 1836-1837, 1848 (Volume [4])
  Account book, Stony Point, sales of haberdashery tobacco, gun powder, flints etc.; with copy book or letter book, North Garden, Albemarle County, 1848, Ann M. Shepherd, A. Anderson, Bettie Anderson, Emma Anderson? Much damaged.
- Account book, Mount Meridian, for sales of cloth and notions, corn, oil, tobacco, etc. 1840-1842 (Volume [5])
- Lawyer's fee book 1842-1856, 1862-1865 (Volume [6])
  later years on pages headed Charlottesville, name, S.F. Leake in front.
- Account book or cash book 1858-1863 (Volume [7])
  perhaps that of C.F. Paterson of Charlottesville, a letter to whom is in the book.
- Account book of a painter and glazier and carpenter evidently of Charlottesville 1859-1883 (Volume [8])
  1878 March inventory (?) of hardware items; 1866-1883, miscellaneous penciled notes of A.F Stocker concerned?
- Miller's accounts, perhaps of Thomas Ballard of Albemarle County 1860-1867 (Volume [9])
- Miller's accounts, N.P. 1866-1869 (Volume [10])
- Day book of Wayland and Thompson, Free Union, dry goods, notions, hardware, groceries 1869-1870 (Volume [11])
- Account book [Charlottesville], sales of stationery, books, picture frames 1869-1873 (Volume [12])
- Account book, Charlottesville, stationery, books, cards, papers 1870-1873 (Volume [13])
- Account book, N.P., recording payments to workmen in money and goods, frequently brandy 1871 (Volume [14])
- Account book of T.L. Michie as assigned bankrupt, Charlottesville 1871-1879 (Volume [15])
- Account book, N.P., sales of corn, bacon, potatoes, salt, cloth [1872]-1874 (Volume [16])
- List of voters in the corporation of Charlottesville, VA 1871-1874 (Volume [17])
  as made by George P. Crank, Registrar, 26 May. Voters listed by name, age, occupation, place and length of residence. Inserted: Notice 25 Sept. 1874 of registration dates; Notes 22 Sept. 1874 purging of registration books, those removed listed by name.
- Day book of [G.W.?] Spooner and [S.M.?] Keller, Hardware merchants of Charlottesville, VA. 1873-1874 (Volume [18])
- Day book of Spooner and Keller, Charlottesville 1875 (Volume [19])
- Bank book of J.W.B. McAllister, in Account with Farmers and Merchants Bank 1875-1877 (Volume [20])
- Day book of Spooner and Keller, Charlottesville 1876 (Volume [21])
- Day book of F.D. Brockman, tailor, of Charlottesville 1876-1884 (Volume [22])
- Ledger of a grocer, evidently of Charlottesville, J.W.B. McAllister? 1877-1878 (Volume [23])
- Inventory of stock, J.W.B. McAllister 1879 (Volume [24])
- Police reports, Charlottesville, John L. Walters, chief of police 1893-1894 (Volume [25])
- Police records, evidently made in Charlottesville 1894-1895 (Volume [26])
- Time book for threshing, [Seamands and Marshall], probably Albemarle County 1880-1881 (Volume [27])